A Guide to the Hunter T. Stagg Papers, 1917-1981
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Hunter T. Stagg Papers, 1917-1981
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 261
2.5 linear feet
Hunter T. Stagg
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection was donated to the the Special Collections and Archives Department by Mr. Robert Saylor (widower of Stagg's niece Charlotte Nance Saylor) in November 1988. Edgar MacDonald provided additional material. Also, a collection of correspondence from Mrs. Elizabeth Norfleet was deposited in February 1994.
Biographical/Historical Information
Hunter Taylor Stagg was born in the city of Richmond the younger son of Thomas E. and Sarah Stagg on 29 May 1895. Kicked in the head by a horse at the age of seven, Stagg became prone to seizures later in life. Stagg attended the Richmond school run by John Peyton McGuire and in 1921 joined with three other "literary minded" individuals (Mary Dallas Street, Emily Clark (Balch) and Margaret Freeman, who married James Branch Cabell in 1950) to establish The Reviewer, a literary magazine.
"Hunter Stagg was an avid literary lionizer, the one of the four who sought meetings with writers for the thrill of associating with creative artists. His handsome appearance, his considerable charm, his genuine appreciation for writing aided him in establishing the friendships he cherished including that of Cabell. Carl Van Vechten, leader of avant-garde cultural circles in New York, responded to Hunter's appeal and opened literary doors for him." -- from the Ellen Glasgow Newsletter #15 which also provides extensive lists of acquaintances met during these years.
The Reviewer moved to North Carolina in 1924 and Stagg held several reviewing positions in Richmond before moving to Washington, D.C. in March 1938 to live with his sister, Helen Winston, and her family. He lived with Mrs. Winston until her death in the late 1940s. After spending some time in New York with Margaret Freeman recuperating from his sister's death, Stagg returned to D.C. and got a job managing a bookstore.
Stagg only worked intermittently throughout his life and was prone to alcoholism. Chronically without funds, Stagg forfeited a portion of his library and his furnishings when he did not meet the storage payments. He was eventually committed to St. Elizabeth's in Washington, D.C. and died there, 23 December 1960. He was buried in the Stagg family section of Hollywood Cemetery. As of 2002, his grave had no marker or tombstone.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains correspondence, notes, typescripts, reviews, bills and miscellaneous materials dating from 1917 to 1981. The bulk of the collection focuses on correspondence throughout the 1920s and 1930s, especially that of James Branch Cabell and Carl Van Vechten (including copies of letters written to Van Vechten from Stagg obtained from Yale University by Edgar MacDonald). Other notable correspondents include: Essie Robeson (wife of Paul Robeson, see 3.5), Majorie K. Rawlings, Tom Rutherfurd (Rutherfoord), Gertrude Stein, Alice Toklas, Frances Newman, Langston Hughes, Ben Ray Redman, Ellen Glasgow, and Montgomery Evans. Much of the Evans correspondence are copies of letters from Stagg to Evans from the Morris Library, Southern Illinois University. These were provided by Dr. Edgar MacDonald during his research of Hunter Stagg.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged alphabetically within each series.
Contents List
- Stagg Materials, n.d. 1917-1976
  - Articles and Reviews, n.d. 1919, 1927 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - American Storage Company 1948-1949 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Correspondence--General, n.d. (Box-folder 1.3)
    1917, 1924-1925, 1927, 1933, 1937, 1947-1948, 1952-1953, 1956, 1976
  - Correspondence--Alastair (Hanael), n.d. 1925-1926, 1932-1933 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Correspondence-Cabell, James Branch, n.d. (Box-folder 1.5)
    1921, 1924, 1935, 1938, 1940-1941, 1943, 1946, 1948-1952
  - Correspondence--Cabell, Ballard 1951-1952 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Correspondence--Cabell, Margaret Freeman 1949-1953 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Correspondence--Davis, Beale 1923-1924 (Box-folder 1.7(1))
  - Correspondence--Glasgow, Ellen (Box-folder 1.8)
    1921, 1925, 1938, 1944
  - Correspondence--Evans, Montgomery (mostly from Stagg), n.d. 1923-1924 (Box-folder 1.9)
  - Correspondence--Evans, Montogomery (mostly from Stagg) (Box-folder 2.1)
    1926-1926, 1935, 1950-1951
  - Correspondence--Hughes, Langston (Box-folder 2.2(2))
    Letters were pasted in the following Books from Stagg's Library: from The Weary Blues, a letter dated 12/1/26, and from Fine Clothes to the Jew a letter dated 2/10/27
  - Correspondence--Newman, Frances 1925 (Box-folder 2.2)
    See also Frances Newman's Letter, pasted in are two letters from Newman
  - Correspondence--Norfleet, Elizabeth (from Stagg) 1938, 1940 (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Correspondence--Rawlings, Majorie K. 1953 (Box-folder 2.3(3))
  - Correspondence--Redman, Ben Ray 1921 (Box-folder 2.4)
  - Correspondence--Stein, Gertrude and Toklas, Alice 1924, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 2.5)
  - Correspondence--Sympathy 1938 (Box-folder 2.6)
  - Correspondence--Troubetzkoy, Amelie 1921 (Box-folder 2.7)
  - Correspondence--Van Vechten, Carl, n.d. (Box-folder 2.8)
  - Correspondence--Van Vechten, Carl 1923 (Box-folder 2.9)
    Includes a letter that was pasted in Stagg's copy of The BlindBow-Boy
  - Correspondence--Van Vechten, Carl 1924 (Box-folder 2.10)
  - Correspondence--Van Vechten, Carl 1925 (Box-folder 2.11)
  - Correspondence--Van Vechten, Carl 1926 (Box-folder 3.1)
  - Correspondence--Van Vechten, Carl 1927-1930 (Box-folder 3.2)
  - Correspondence--Van Vechten, Carl 1931 (Box-folder 3.3)
  - Correspondence--Van Vechten, Carl 1932 (Box-folder 3.4)
  - Correspondence--Van Vechten, Carl 1933-1934, 1938 (Box-folder 3.5)
  - Correspondence--Woodford, Jack 1950, 1953 (Box-folder 3.6)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. 1976 (Box-folder 3.7)
  - Notes, n.d. (Box-folder 3.8)
  - Passport 1925 (Box-folder 3.9)
  - Playbills, n.d. (Box-folder 4.1)
  - Portraits (photocopies), n.d. (Box-folder 4.2)
  - Publications--miscellaneous journals, some of which have articles written by Stagg (Box-folder 4.3)
  - Publications-- The Absence of Mr. Cabell (Box-folder 4.4)
  - Publications-- Cabell: A Reconsideration (Box-folder 4.5)
  - Publications-- Das Flammende Tal (Box-folder 4.6)
  - Taxes 1950 (Box-folder 4.7)
  - Typescript-- The Family of Julia Ambler (Box-folder 4.8)
  - Typescript-- Fenris (Box-folder 4.9)
  - Typescript-- From the Left Hand Corner of the Page (Box-folder 4.10)
  - Typescript-- From the Left Hand Corner of the Page version B (Box-folder 4.11)
  - Typescript-- Murder. A Gamble in Revenge (Box-folder 4.12)
  - Inserts from Stagg's library of books written by James Branch Cabell (Box-folder 4.13-4.30)
  - Inserts from Stagg's library, miscellaneous authors (Box-folder 4-A.1)
  - Stagg Library-Book Description (inscribed, pages, inserts...) (Box-folder 4-A.2)
- Associated Materials, n.d. 1976-1981
  Much of this material contains correspondence and other items collected by Dr. Edgar MacDonald who in the 1970s researched the life and work of Stagg.
  - Associated materials 1976 (Box-folder 5.1)
  - Associated materials 1977 (Box-folder 5.2)
  - Associated materials 1978 (Box-folder 5.3)
  - Associated materials 1979, 1981 (Box-folder 5.4)
  - Evans, Montgomery--Diary (photocopy) (Box-folder 5.5)
  - Ellen Glasgow Newsletter (about Stagg) (Box-folder 5.6)
  - Firbank, Ronald (Box-folder 5.7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 5.8)
- Correspondence to Elizabeth Norfleet from Hunter Sag and to Fillmore and Elizabeth Nor fleet from H.. Cooper, n.d. 1938-1979
  - Correspondence--Sag, Hunter ( to Elizabeth Nor fleet), n.d. 1938-1940 (Box-folder 5.9)
  - Correspondence--Cooper, H.. (to Fillmore and Elizabeth Nor fleet) 1961-1979 (Box-folder 5.10)